So, I'd like to end with a summary of what
I've looked at today, and some recommendations.
The figures show that sales are strongly seasonal,
and that customers depend on good information
on the showroom floor. So I'd like to recommend
we concentrate on discounting in the off-seasons,
and spend more time on briefing our sales
representatives.
That's all I have for now. Are there any questions?
You mentioned that the sales figures may also
reflect economic trends. Can you expand on
that?
Well, we are always going to depend on the
economy. As I understand it, we can look forward
to an improvement this year. Does that answer
your question?
Are you saying we're in for a period of growth?
Well, I'm afraid that's a bit outside my area
of expertise, but that's what the papers are
suggesting.
If you believe it.
You suggested that we might be spending too
much on advertising. Can you clarify that?
It's hard to quantify without better data.
Sorry. Could you repeat that?
We don't have the figures to really know how
effective our advertising is.
In my experience you can't do without advertising.
Time for one last question.
I have one.
Yes John?
Is it time for coffee?
Okay, we'll wrap up now. Thank you for your
input everyone.
Thank you.
Today we're looking at how to end a presentation,
and how to deal with questions. Let's look
first at how Barbara concludes, or finishes
her presentation.
I'd like to end with a summary of what I've
looked at today, and some recommendations.
Barbara says she'd like to end with a summary,
and some recommendations.
When ending a presentation or a talk, you
may do this with a summary - this is a short
statement of your main points - with a conclusion,
which is a result of all the information you've
presented, or recommendations, which are things
you think should be done. In all cases, they
should be clear and concise, or not too long.
Practise with Barbara some phrases you can
use to introduce your final points.
I'd like to end with some recommendations
I'll finish with a summary
What can we conclude from all this?
Listen to the difference between the summary
and the recommendations.
The figures show that sales are strongly seasonal,
and that customers depend on good information
on the showroom floor. So I'd like to recommend
we concentrate on discounting in the off-seasons,
and spend more time on briefing our sales
representatives.
Her summary consists of the main points from
her talk about sales figures. There are two
points. Her recommendations are what she thinks
the company should do in the future, and there
are two of these as well. Here are some phrases
you can use to introduce a summary and recommendations.
In summary
To summarise
I'd like to recommend that
My recommendations are
Let's look at how Barbara finishes her talk,
and asks for questions.
That's all I have for now. Are there any questions?
Here's Barbara with some useful phrases for
you to practise if asking for questions.
Are there any questions?
I'll answer any questions now.
Does anyone have any questions?
At the end of a talk, you may ask for questions,
or for comments, or for a general discussion.
You need to let your audience know what you
want them to do, like this:
Are there any comments?
I'd like to open it up for discussion.
Let's look at how Denise asks a question.
You mentioned that the sales figures may also
reflect economic trends. Can you expand on
that?
Denise does two things. First she re-states
something Barbara said, then she asks her
to expand on it, or say more about it. It's
a good idea when asking a question to state
what you think the speaker said, so everyone
knows what the question is about.
You might say
You mentioned that
You suggested that
You stated that
In the question you can ask the speaker to
respond in different ways. Denise asks her
to expand, but she could also clarify, or
make clearer, or explain further. Practise
some phrases you can use for this:
Can you expand on that?
Can you clarify that?
Could you explain that a bit further?
Listen to how Barbara answers Denise's question:
Well, we are always going to depend on the
economy. As I understand it, we can look forward
to an improvement this year. Does that answer
your question?
In her answer Barbara uses the phrase, "As
I understand it". By using this phrase she
is signalling that this is not really her
area of expertise. She is getting her information
from somewhere else. You could also use phrases
like:
As far as I know, or
My information is that
Notice that she also checks whether Denise
is satisfied with her answer by saying:
Does that answer your question?
If she wanted to, Denise could ask a further
question, but Tan does it for her.
Are you saying we're in for a period of growth?
Well, I'm afraid that's a bit outside my area
of expertise, but that's what the papers are
suggesting.
Tan is asking for clarification. He wants
Barbara to say more about her point. He does
this by checking that he has understood her.
Practise with Tan some phrases you can use
to ask for clarification.
Are you saying
So you're saying that
So, are you suggesting that
If I follow you, you're suggesting that
Let's look at some more questions now.
You suggested that we might be spending too
much on advertising. Can you clarify that?
It's hard to quantify without better data.
Sorry. Could you repeat that?
We don't have the figures to really know how
effective our advertising is.
Notice that, as before, Denise restates what
she thinks Barbara said, by saying, "You suggested
that," then asks her to clarify, by saying,
"Can you clarify that?"
and Tan asks her to repeat something simply
by asking, "Could you repeat that?" Notice
too that when Barbara answers Tan, she uses
different words. If someone asks you to repeat,
or clarify, it's better to rephrase, than
simply say the same thing again. Notice how
Denise puts in her own comment.
In my experience you can't do without advertising.
This is Denise's comment, or opinion, not
a question. She shows this by starting, "in
my experience". She could also have said,
"in my opinion" or "as I understand it".
Let's see now how Barbara finishes her presentation.
Time for one last question.
I have one.
Yes John?
Is it time for coffee?
Okay, we'll wrap up now. Thank you for your
input everyone.
Thank you.
The person giving the talk is in control,
so she needs to signal that she is finished.
She does this by saying, "Time for one last
question."
Practise some phrases you could use to end
a presentation.
Time for one last question
Are there any more questions?
I think we'll wrap it up now
So remember, after a talk, give a summary
and perhaps some recommendations or conclusions.
Ask for questions or comments. When asking
questions, state what you understood from
the speaker first, and then say what you want
them to do - clarify, or explain, or expand.
Well, that about wraps us up for today. Thanks
for listening, and I'll see you next time
on The Business of English.